<refentry>
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>epicsGraph</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1tcl</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>epicsgraph</refname>
        <refpurpose>
            Wrap a BLT graph with code for plotting epics channels against each other.
        </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
    <programlisting>
<command>
package require epicsGraph
controlwidget::epicsStripChart  <replaceable>name ?options?</replaceable>
<replaceable>name</replaceable> addseries <replaceable>sname x-channel y-channel interval ?options?</replaceable>
<replaceable>name</replaceable> removeseries <replaceable> sname</replaceable>
</command>
    </programlisting>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            This widget is a thin wrapping of the BLT Graph widget.  The wrapping allows you
            to easily create graphs of epics channel pairs (e.g. one channel on the x axis, one on
            the y axis).  Any number of pairs of channels can be plotted on the same widget if desired
            with line colors symbol shapes and line types distinguishing between them.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>OPTIONS</title>
        <para>
            All options for the blt::graph widget are supported and passed to that widget without
            any interpretation.  See the summary (section blt::graph summary) below or alternatively:
            <ulink url="http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_graph">http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_graph</ulink>
            for a full description of that widget.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>METHODS</title>
        <para>
            All blt::graph widget methods are supported.  See the summary
            (section blt::graph  summary) below or alternatively,
            <ulink url="http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_graph">http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_graph</ulink>
            The blt::graph widget methods are passed without any interpretation on to that widget.
        </para>
        <para>
            In addition the following methods are also defined:
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command><replaceable>name</replaceable> addseries <replaceable>sname x-channel y-channel interval ?options?</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Adds a data series to the graph.  A data series consists of a
                            blt::graph element that displayse the data and
                            <classname>channnelPairHistory</classname> object to automatically maintain
                            the element's data.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            <parameter>sname</parameter> is the name of the series to create.  It must
                            be unique and will also be used as the blt::graph element name.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            <parameter>x-channel y-channel</parameter>
                            are the names of the EPICS process variables that will be the X and Y
                            parameters of the data series respectively.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            <parameter>interval</parameter> is the number of milliseconds between
                            samples on the plot.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            <parameter>options</parameter> are optional option value pairs that are passed
                            as is to the blt::graph element add command and can be used to configure the
                            appearance of the data series e.g.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The command returns the name of the channel pair history object which can be saved
                            and manipulated.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command><replaceable>name</replaceable> removeseries <replaceable> sname</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Removes the series <parameter>sname</parameter> from the graph and
                            destroys the channel pair history object that was created for it.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>channelPairHistory objects</title>
            <para>
                <classname>channelPairHistory</classname> objects are used to keep track of
                and manage the automatic update of data series.  While intended for use with the
                epicsGraph widget, you may also find them useful in your applications.  This section
                therefore summarizes the capabilities of the <classname>channelPairHistory</classname>
                snit::type.
            </para>
            <refsect2>
                <title>OPTIONS</title>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-period</option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Specifies the milliseconds between data updates</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-xchannel</option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> Name of the x channel.  When used with an epicsGraph
                                to produce a data series, this parameter will be on the x axis.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-ychanel</option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Name of the y channel.  When used with an epicsGraph to produce
                                a data series, this parameter will be on the y axis.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-timebase</option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>[clock seconds] at which the data series start.  When the
                                data are retrieved from the object, the times associated with
                                each data points are offsets relative to this time.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </refsect2>
            <refsect2>
                <title>METHODS</title>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><methodname>clear</methodname></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Clears the entire data series.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><methodname>clearfirst</methodname> <parameter>n</parameter></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Clears the first <parameter>n</parameter> data points in the series.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><methodname>keep</methodname> <parameter>n</parameter></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Keeps only the first <parameter>n</parameter> data points in a series.
                                This restriction is enforced on each update of the series.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><methodname>names</methodname></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                The data series is maintained in a set of three
                                <classname>blt::vector</classname>
                                objects.  This returns the names of the three vectors.
                                The names are returned as a three element list. The first element of
                                the list is the name of the time vector.  The second element
                                of th elist is the name of the x parameter vector. The third
                                element of the list is the name of the y parameter vector.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><methodname>get</methodname></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Returns the data stored in the series.  The data are returned as
                                a list of data points. Each data point is a three element list consisting
                                of (in order), the time relative to the <option>-timebase</option>
                                time, the x parameter value at that time, and the y parameter value
                                at that time.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </refsect2>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>blt::graph summary</title>
        <para>
            See
            <ulink url="http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_graph">http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_graph</ulink>
            for a full description of the blt::graph widget.  This section provides a summary of the
            more useful features of the widget in an attempt to make this manpage close to self contained
            for most uses of the widget.
        </para>
        <para>
            The blt::graph widget is a graph that plots X-Y data.  The graph widget can be thought
            of as having many independently configurable components.  Configuring each component can
            determine how the graph will appear.
        </para>
        <refsect2>
            <title>OPTIONS</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-height</option> <parameter>measure</parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            sets the requested height of the widget.  This can be any valid
                            Tk measurement.  The default is 4i
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-title</option> <parameter>text</parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Sets the title to <parameter>text</parameter>.
                            If <parameter>text</parameter> is "", no title will be displayed.
                       </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-width</option> <parameter>measure</parameter></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Specifies the requested width of the widget.  The default is 5i.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>COMPONENTS</title>
            <para>
                The graph widget can be thought of as made up of several components.
                Each component can be indepdendently configured and, in some cases
                several components of each type can be created.
                This section summarizes the components and what they do.  Subsequent
                sections will describe the most useful options of the most used components.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>axis</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The graph has four standard axes (x, x2, y, and y2), but you can create
                            and display any number of axes.
                            Axes control what region of data is displayed and how the data is scaled.
                            Each  axis  consists  of  the
                            axis  line, title, major and minor ticks, and tick labels.
                            Tick labels display the value at each major
                            tick.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>crosshairs</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Cross hairs are used to position the mouse pointer relative
                            to the X and Y coordinate axes. Two perpendicular  lines,
                            intersecting  at the current location of the mouse, extend
                            across the plotting area to
                            the coordinate axes.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>element</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            An element represents a set of data points. Elements can be
                            plotted with a symbol at  each  data  point
                            and  lines  connecting  the points.  The appearance of the
                            element, such as its symbol, line width, and
                            color is configurable. Data series of epics channels are implemented
                            as elements.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>grid</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Extends the major and minor ticks of the X-axis and/or
                            Y-axis across the plotting area.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>legend</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The legend displays the name and symbol of each data
                            element.  The legend can be drawn in any margin or
                            in the plotting area.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>marker</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Markers  are used annotate or highlight areas of the
                            graph. For example, you could use a polygon marker
                            to fill an area under a curve, or a text marker to
                            label a particular data point. Markers come in various forms:
                            text strings, bitmaps, connected line segments, images,
                            polygons, or embedded widgets.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>pen</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Pens  define  attributes  (both symbol and line style)
                            for elements.  Data elements use pens to specify
                            how they should be drawn.  A data element may use many
                            pens at once.  Here, the particular pen used for
                            a  data  point  is  determined  from each element's weight
                            vector (see the element's -weight and -style
                            options).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>postscript</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The widget can generate encapsulated PostScript output.
                            This component has several options to configure
                            how the PostScript is generated.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>axis</title>
            <para>
               Four  coordinate  axes  are automatically created: two X-coordinate axes
               (x and x2) and two Y-coordinate axes (y,
                and y2).  By default, the axis x is located in the bottom margin, y
                in the left margin, x2 in the top margin, and
                y2 in the right margin.
            </para>
            <para>
                An  axis consists of the axis line, title, major and minor
                ticks, and tick labels.  Major ticks are drawn at uniform intervals
                along the axis.  Each tick is labeled with its coordinate value.  Minor
                ticks are drawn at uniform
                intervals within major ticks.
            </para>
            <para>
                The  range of the axis controls what region of data is plotted.
                Data points outside the minimum and maximum limits of the axis are
                not plotted.  By default, the minimum and maximum limits are
                determined from  the  data,  but
                you can reset either limit.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can have several axes. To create an axis, invoke the axis
                component and its create operation.
                <programlisting>
# Create a new axis called "tempAxis"
.g axis create tempAxis
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                You  map  data  elements  to  an axis using the element's -mapy and -mapx
                configuration options. They specify the
                coordinate axes an element is mapped onto.
                <programlisting>
# Now map the tempAxis data to this axis.
.g element create "e1" -xdata $x -ydata $y -mapy tempAxis
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                Any number of axes can be displayed simultaneously. They are drawn
                in the margins surrounding the plotting  area.
                The  default axes x and y are drawn in the bottom and left
                margins. The axes x2 and y2 are drawn in top and right
                margins.  By default, only x and y are shown. Note that the axes
                can have different scales.
            </para>
            <para>
                To display a different axis or more than one axis, you invoke one of
                the  following  components:  xaxis,  yaxis,
                x2axis,  and  y2axis.   Each component has a use operation that designates
                the axis (or axes) to be drawn in that
                corresponding margin: xaxis in the bottom, yaxis in the left, x2axis
                in the top, and y2axis in the right.
                <programlisting> 
# Display the axis tempAxis in the left margin.
.g yaxis use tempAxis
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                The use operation takes a list of axis names as its last argument.  This is
                the list of axes to be drawn in  this
                margin.
            </para>
            <para>
                You  can configure axes in many ways. The axis scale can be
                linear or logarithmic.  The values along the axis can
                either monotonically increase or decrease.  If you need
                custom tick labels, you can specify a  Tcl  procedure  to
                format  the  label any way you wish.  You can control how
                ticks are drawn, by changing the major tick interval or
                the number of minor ticks.  You can define non-uniform tick intervals,
                such as for time-series plots.
            </para>
            <para>
                Axis components are manipulated using an ensemble of widgets commands (methods)
                of the form:
                <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>pathName</replaceable> axis <replaceable>subcommand</replaceable> &hellip;</command>
                </programlisting>
                The most useful of the <replaceable>subcommand</replaceable>s  will be described below.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                <term>cget <replaceable>axisName option</replaceable></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Returns the current value of the option given by option
                        for axisName.  Option may be any option  described
                        below for the axis configure operation.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>configure <replaceable>axisName option value</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Sets a new value for a configuration option for the axis
                            <parameter>axisName</parameter>.  <replaceable>option</replaceable>
                            and value are described in the 'most useful list of options' below:
                        </para>
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-color</option> <replaceable>color</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Sets the color of the axis and tick labels.
                                            The default is black.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-descending</option> <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Indicates whether the values along the axis
                                            are monotonically increasing or decreasing.  If boolean
                                            is true, the axis values will be decreasing.
                                            The default is 0.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-logscale</option> <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Indicates whether the scale of the axis is
                                            logarithmic or linear.  If boolean is true, the axis  is
                                            logarithmic.  The default scale is linear.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-majorticks</option> <replaceable>majorlist</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Specifies where to display major axis ticks.
                                            You can use this option to display ticks at  nonuniform
                                            intervals.   <replaceable>majorlist</replaceable> is a list of
                                            axis coordinates designating the location of major ticks.
                                            No minor ticks are drawn.  If
                                            <replaceable>majorList</replaceable> is "", major
                                            ticks  will  be  automatically  computed.  The
                                            default is "".
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-max</option> <replaceable>value</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Sets  the maximum limit of axisName.
                                            Any data point greater than value is not displayed.
                                            If value
                                            is "", the maximum limit is calculated using the largest
                                            data value.  The default is "".  Note that this calculation
                                            is performed again as data elements change in time.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-min</option> <replaceable>value</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Sets the minimum limit of axisName.
                                            Any data point less than value is not displayed.
                                            If  value  is
                                            "", the minimum limit is calculated using the
                                            smallest data value.  The default is "".
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-minorticks</option> <replaceable>minorList</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Specifies  where  to  display  minor axis ticks.
                                            You can use this option to display minor ticks at
                                            non-uniform intervals. <replaceable>MinorList</replaceable>
                                            is a list of real values, ranging from 0.0 to 1.0,
                                            designating the
                                            placement  of  a  minor  tick.   No minor ticks are
                                            drawn if the -majortick option is also set.  If
                                            minorList is "", minor ticks will be automatically
                                            computed. The default is "".
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-stepsize</option> <replaceable>value</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Specifies  the  interval  between  major axis ticks.
                                            If value isn't a valid interval (must be less
                                            than the axis range), the request is ignored and the
                                            step size is automatically calculated.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-subdivisions</option> <replaceable>number</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Indicates how many minor axis ticks are to be drawn.
                                            For example, if <replaceable>number</replaceable> is two,
                                            only one minor
                                            tick is drawn.  If <replaceable>number</replaceable>
                                            is one, no minor ticks are displayed.  The default is 2.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-title</option> <replaceable>text</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Sets the title of the axis. If
                                            <replaceable>text</replaceable>
                                            is "", no axis title will be displayed.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>create</command> <replaceable>axisName ?options...?</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Creates a new axis by the name <replaceable>axisName</replaceable>.
                            No axis by the same name can already exist. 
                            <replaceable>?options...?</replaceable> are option value pairs described
                            above under the <command>configure</command> subcommand.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>delete</command> <replaceable>axisName</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Deletes  the  named  axes.  An  axis  is not really
                            deleted until it is not longer in use, so it's safe to
                            delete axes mapped to elements.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>names</command> <replaceable>?pattern?</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Returns  a  list of axes matching zero or more patterns.
                            If no <replaceable>pattern</replaceable> argument is give,
                            the names of all axes are returned.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>  
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>element</title>
            <para>
                An element is what we refer to as a data series.  Elements are displayed as
                a set of X/Y points on the surface of the graph, limited by the axes they are
                associated with.  The points can be connected by lines that have various line
                styles an doclors (see pen components as well).
            </para>
            <para>
                When new data elements are created, they are automatically added
                to a list of displayed elements.    The  display
                list controls what elements are drawn and in what order.
            </para>
            <para>
                The following operations are the most useful ones available for elements.
                All are of the form:
                <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>pathName</replaceable> element <replaceable>subcommand ...</replaceable></command>
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>cget <replaceable>elemNamme option</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Returns  the  current value of the element configuration
                            option given by <replaceable>option</replaceable>.
                            <replaceable>Option</replaceable> may be any of the
                            options described below for the element configure operation.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>configure <replaceable>elemName ... ?option...</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Queries  or modifies the configuration options for elements.
                            Several elements can be modified at the same
                            time. If <replaceable>option</replaceable> isn't specified,
                            a list describing all the current options for
                            <replaceable>elemName</replaceable> is  returned.   If an
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable>  is specified, but not its value,
                            then a list describing the option
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable> is returned.  If one or more
                            option and value pairs are specified, then for each pair, the
                            element option <replaceable>option</replaceable> is set to
                            <replaceable>value</replaceable>.   The
                            following options are are the most commonly used ones valid for elements.
                            <variablelist>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-color</option> <replaceable>color</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Sets the color of the traces connecting the data points.
                                            </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-dashes</option> <replaceable>dashlist</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Sets the dash style of element line.
                                            <replaceable>DashList</replaceable>
                                            is a list of up to 11 numbers that alternately represent
                                            the lengths of the dashes and gaps on the element line.
                                            Each number must  be  between  1  and
                                            255.  If <replaceable>dashList</replaceable> is "",
                                            the lines will be solid.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-label</option> <replaceable>text</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            Sets the element's label in the legend.
                                            If text is "", the element will have no entry
                                            in the  legend.  The default label is the element's name.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-pen</option> <replaceable>penname</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>Set the pen to use for this element.  For more information
                                            about pens, see the pen component described later in this
                                            document.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                                <varlistentry>
                                    <term><option>-symbol</option> <replaceable>symbol</replaceable></term>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                           Specifies  the  symbol for data points.
                                           <replaceable>Symbol</replaceable> can be either
                                            <literal>square</literal>,
                                            <literal>circle</literal>, <literal>diamond</literal>,
                                            <literal>plus</literal>, <literal>cross</literal>,
                                            <literal>splus</literal>, <literal>scross</literal>,
                                            <literal>triangle</literal>,
                                            <literal>""</literal> (where no symbol is drawn),
                                            or a  bitmap.   Bitmaps  are  specified  as
                                           "source  ?mask?",  where
                                           <replaceable>source</replaceable> is the name of
                                            the bitmap, and <replaceable>mask</replaceable> is
                                            the bitmap's optional mask.
                                            The default is <literal>circle</literal>. 
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </varlistentry>
                            </variablelist>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>exists <replaceable>elemName</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Returns 1 if an element
                            <replaceable>elemName</replaceable> currently exists and 0 otherwise.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>element names <replaceable>?pattern?...</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Returns  the  elements matching one or more pattern.
                            If no pattern is given, the names of all elements is
                            returned.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>   
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>grid</title>
            <para>
                Grid  lines  extend  from  the  major and minor ticks of
                each axis horizontally or vertically across the plotting
                area.  While there are many options and operations associated with
                grid lines, the most common ones are:
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                <term><command>grid on</command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Turns on the display the grid lines.
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>grid off</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Turns off the display the grid lines.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
            <title>legend</title>
            <para>
               The  legend  displays  a  list of the data elements.  Each 
               entry consists of the element's symbol and label.  The
               legend can appear in any margin (the default location is in the
               right margin). 
               It can also  be  positioned  anywhere within the plotting area.
            </para>
            <para>
               Legend operations are of the form:
               <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>pathName</replaceable> legend <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command>
               </programlisting>
               The most frequently used legend operations are:
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>cget
                    <replaceable>option</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Returns  the  current value of a legend
                            configuration option.  
                            <replaceable>Option</replaceable> may be any option described below in
                            the legend configure operation.
                         </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>configure
                    <replaceable>?option...?</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Queries or modifies the configuration options for
                           the legend.  
                           If <replaceable>option</replaceable> isn't
                           specified, 
                           a list  describing  the  current  legend options 
                           for <replaceable>pathName</replaceable> is returned.  
                           If <replaceable>option</replaceable> is specified, 
                           but not <replaceable>value</replaceable>, then a
                           list describing <replaceable>option</replaceable> 
                           is returned.  If one or more option and value pairs 
                           are specified,  then  for  each
                           pair, the legend option 
                           <replaceable>option</replaceable> is set to 
                           <replaceable>value</replaceable>.  The following 
                           options (and others) are valid for the legend.
                       </para>
                       <variablelist>
                           <varlistentry>
                               <term><option>-hide
                               <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                               <listitem>
                                  <para>
                                       Indicates whether the legend should be 
                                       displayed. If 
                                       <replaceable>boolean</replaceable> is 
                                       <literal>true</literal>, the legend will 
                                       not be  drawn. The default is
                                       <literal>no</literal>. 
                                  </para>
                               </listitem>
                           </varlistentry>
                           <varlistentry>
                              <term><option>-position
                              <replaceable>pos</replaceable></option></term>
                              <listitem>
                                  <para>
                                       Specifies  where  the  legend  is
                                       drawn.  The 
                                       <option>-anchor</option> option also
                                       affects 
                                       where the legend is positioned.  
                                       If <replaceable>pos</replaceable> is 
                                       <literal>left</literal>,
                                       <literal>left</literal>, 
                                       <literal>top</literal>, 
                                       or <literal>bottom</literal>, the legend 
                                       is drawn in the specified margin.  
                                       If <replaceable>pos</replaceable>
                                       is  <literal>plotarea</literal>,  
                                       then the legend is drawn inside the
                                       plotting 
                                       area at a particular anchor.  If 
                                       <replaceable>pos</replaceable> is
                                       in the form "@x,y", where x and y are 
                                       the window coordinates, the legend is 
                                       drawn in  the  plotting area at the 
                                       specified coordinates.  The default is right.
                                 </para>
                             </listitem>
                         </varlistentry>
                     </variablelist>
                   </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
             </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
        <refsect2>
           <title>Pen</title>
           <para>
               Pens  define attributes (both symbol and line style) for
               elements. Pens mirror the configuration options of data
               elements that pertain to how symbols and lines are drawn. 
               Data elements use  pens  to  determine  how  they  are
               drawn.   A  data element may use several pens at once.  
               In this case, the pen used for a particular data point is
               determined from each element's weight vector (see the element's 
               -weight and -style options).
           </para>
           <para>
              One pen, called activeLine, is automatically created.  It's
               used as the default active pen for elements.  So  you
               can change the active attributes for all elements by simply reconfiguring this pen.
               <programlisting>
<command>.g pen configure "activeLine" -color green</command>
               </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                 You can create and use several pens. To create a pen, 
                 invoke the pen component and its create operation.
                 <programlisting>
<command>.g pen create myPen</command>
                 </programlisting>
             </para>
             <para> 
                You map pens to a data element using either the element's 
                -pen or -activepen options.
                <programlisting>
<command>.g element create "line1" -xdata $x -ydata $tempData \
                 -pen myPen</command>
                </programlisting>
             </para>
             <para>
                An  element  can  use several pens at once. This is done by
                specifying the name of the pen in the element's style
                list (see the -styles option).
                <programlisting>
<command>.g element configure "line1" -styles { myPen 2.0 3.0 }</command>
                </programlisting>
             </para>
             <para>
                 This says that any data point with a weight between 
                 2.0 and 3.0 is to be drawn using the pen  myPen.   All  other
                 points are drawn with the element's default attributes.
             </para>
             <para>
               The following operations are available for pen components, and are of the
               form:
               <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>pathName</replaceable> pen <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command>
               </programlisting>
               Descriptions start with the <replaceable>operation</replaceable>.
             </para>
             <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>cget <replaceable>penName option</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Returns  the  current value of the option
                            given by <replaceable>option</replaceable> for
                            <replaceable>penName</replaceable>.
                            <replaceable>Option</replaceable> may be any
                            option described
                            below for the pen configure operation.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>configure <replaceable>penName ?penName... ?option...?</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Queries or modifies the configuration options
                            of penName. Several pens can be modified at once.  If
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable>
                            isn't  specified,  a list describing the current
                            options for penName is returned.  If
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable> is specified,
                            but not <replaceable>value</replaceable>,
                            then a list describing
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable> is returned.
                            If one or more option and value pairs are specified,
                            then  for  each  pair, the pen option
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable> is set to
                            <replaceable>value</replaceable>.  The following options
                            are valid for pens.
                        </para>
                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-color <replaceable>color</replaceable></option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Sets the color of the traces connecting the data points.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-dashes <replaceable>dashList</replaceable></option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Sets the dash style of element line.
                                        <replaceable>DashList</replaceable> is
                                        a list of up to 11 numbers that alternately
                                        represent  the  lengths  of  the dashes and
                                        gaps on the element line.  Each number must
                                        be between 1 and
                                        255.  If
                                        <replaceable>dashList</replaceable> is "", the
                                        lines will be solid.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-symbol <replaceable>symbol</replaceable></option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Specifies the symbol for data points.
                                        Symbol can be either
                                        <literal>square</literal>,
                                        <literal>circle</literal>,
                                        <literal>diamond</literal>,
                                        <literal>plus</literal>,
                                        <literal>cross</literal>,
                                        <literal>splus</literal>,
                                        <literal>scross</literal>,
                                        <literal>triangle</literal>,
                                        <literal>""</literal>  (where  no symbol is drawn),
                                        or a bitmap.  Bitmaps are specified as
                                        "source ?mask?", where
                                        <replaceable>source</replaceable> is the name of
                                        the bitmap, and <replaceable>mask</replaceable>
                                        is the  bitmap's  optional  mask.
                                        The default is <literal>circle</literal>.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>create <replaceable>penName ?option value?...</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Creates a new pen by the name
                            <replaceable>penName</replaceable>.
                            No pen by the same name can already exist.
                            <replaceable>Option</replaceable>  and
                            <replaceable>value</replaceable>  are
                            described in above in the pen configure operation.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>delete <replaceable>?penName?...</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Deletes  the named pens. A pen is not really
                            deleted until it is not longer in use, so it's
                            safe to delete
                            pens mapped to elements.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>names <replaceable>?pattern?...</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Returns a list of pens matching zero or more patterns.  If no
                            pattern argument is give, the names  of  all
                            pens are returned.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>         
             </variablelist>
       </refsect2>
       <refsect2>
           <title>postscript</title>
           <para>
                The  graph  can generate encapsulated PostScript output.
                There are several configuration options you can specify
                to control how the plot will be generated.  You can change
                the page dimensions and borders.  The plot itself  can
                be  scaled,  centered,  or  rotated  to  landscape.   The
                PostScript output can be written directly to a file or
                returned through the interpreter.
           </para>
           <para>
                Postscript operations all have the form:
                <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>pathName</replaceable> postscript <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command>
                </programlisting>
                The following postscript operations are available.
           </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>cget <replaceable>option</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Returns the current value of the postscript
                            option given by
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable>.
                            <replaceable>Option</replaceable> may be
                            any  option  described
                            below for the postscript <command>configure</command> operation.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>configure <replaceable>?option value?...</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Queries  or  modifies  the  configuration options
                            for PostScript generation.  If
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable> isn't specified, a
                            list describing the current postscript options for
                            <replaceable>pathName</replaceable> is returned.
                            If <replaceable>option</replaceable> is specified, but  not
                            <replaceable>value</replaceable>,  then  a
                            list describing
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable> is returned.
                            If one or more option and value pairs are specified,
                            then for each pair, the postscript option
                            <replaceable>option</replaceable> is set to
                            <replaceable>value</replaceable>.  The following  postscript  options  are
                            available.
                        </para>
                        <variablelist>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-center <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Indicates  whether  the  plot
                                        should be centered on the PostScript page.
                                        If <replaceable>boolean</replaceable> is
                                        false, the
                                        plot will be placed in the upper left corner
                                        of the page.  The default is 1 (true), which centers
                                        the plot on the postscript page.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-colormode <replaceable>mode</replaceable></option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Specifies how to output color information.
                                        <replaceable>Mode</replaceable> must be either
                                        <literal>color</literal> (for full color output),
                                        <literal>gray</literal>
                                        (convert  all  colors  to their gray-scale equivalents) or
                                        <literal>mono</literal> (
                                        convert foreground colors to black
                                        and background colors to white).
                                        The default mode is color.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-landscape <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        If <replaceable>boolean</replaceable> is
                                        <literal>true</literal>, this specifies
                                        the printed area is to be rotated 90  degrees.
                                        In  non-rotated
                                        output the X-axis of the printed area runs
                                        along the short dimension of the page (``portrait
                                        orientation); in rotated output the X-axis runs
                                        along the long dimension of  the  page
                                        (``landscape
                                        orientation).  Defaults to 0.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                            <varlistentry>
                                <term><option>-maxpect <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Indicates to scale the plot so that it
                                        fills the PostScript page.  The aspect ratio
                                        of the graph is
                                        still retained.  The default is 0.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </varlistentry>
                        </variablelist>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>output <replaceable>?fileName? ?option value?...</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Outputs a file of encapsulated PostScript.
                            If a <replaceable>fileName</replaceable> argument isn't present,
                            the command returns
                            the
                            PostScript.  If  any  option-value  pairs  are
                            present, they set configuration options controlling how the
                            PostScript is generated.  Option and value can be anything
                            accepted by the postscript configure  operation
                            above.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
       </refsect2>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>EXAMPLES</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    
            
</refentry>
