<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML 4.3//EN"
                      "file:///usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.3/docbookx.dtd"
 []
 >
<book>
<article>
<refentry>
    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>epicsStripChart</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>1tcl</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>
    <refnamediv>
        <refname>epicsStripChart</refname>
        <refpurpose>
            Wrap a BLT stripchart with code for plotting epics channel time evolutions.
        </refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>
    <refsynopsisdiv>
    <programlisting>
<command>
package require epicsStripChart

controlwidget::epicsStripChart  <replaceable>name ?options?</replaceable>
                                
name addchannel <replaceable>channel milliseconds ?options?</replaceable>
                
name removechannel <replaceable>channel</replaceable>
</command>
    </programlisting>
    </refsynopsisdiv>
    <refsect1>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            This widget adds machinery to the BLT Strip chart widget to support adding
            epics channels to a chart.  For a summary of the BLT stripchart widget, see
            the section BLT STRIPCHART below.  For full information about the BLT stripchart
            widget see the online man pages at e.g.
            <ulink url="http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_stripchart">http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_stripchart</ulink>.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>OPTIONS</title>
        <para>
            All BLT stripchart widget options are supported.   For some of the non-standard useful
            options see BLT STRIPCHART below, or the online man page referenced in the DESCRIPTION
            section.
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>METHODS</title>
        <para>
            All blt stripchart methods are supported, in addition to the ones described below.
            For some of the more useful blt stripchart methods, see the section
            BLT STRIPCHART below, or refer to the online manual pages for the stripchart widget
            referred to in the DESCRIPTION section.
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>addchannel <replaceable>name milliseconds ?options?</replaceable></command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Adds the channel <parameter>name</parameter> to the strip chart as a
                        new <firstterm>channelHistory</firstterm> element.   The strip chart
                        will automatically trace the channel value updating every
                        <parameter>milliseconds</parameter> milliseconds.  The
                        optional list of <option>?options</option>, can be any of the options
                        accepted by the BLT stripchart widget's element component.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The method returns a name which is both the name of the new BLT
                        strip chart element and a command that can be used to manipulate the
                        channelHistory object.  For more information about the channelHistory
                        object, see  the section channelHistory OBJECTS below. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>removechannel <replaceable>name</replaceable></command></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Removes the specified channel from the strip chart.  Note that this is
                        the <emphasis>channel name</emphasis> not the name of the
                        channelHistory object returned by the <command>addchannel</command> method.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Removing the specified channel from the strip chart destroys the element
                        created for the trace.  It also destroys the associated channelHistory object
                        and all resources associated with that object.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>channelHistory OBJECTS</title>
        <para>
            Adding a channel to the stripchart creates a new object called a
            <firstterm>channelHistory</firstterm> object and returns the object name
            to the user.  This object also has methods as described in the synopsis below:
            <programlisting>
            <command>
set <replaceable>object</replaceable> [<replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> addchannel <replaceable>name millisecondds ?options?</replaceable>

<replaceable>object</replaceable> clear

<replaceable>object</replaceable> clearfirst <replaceable>points</replaceable>
                                        
<replaceable>object</replaceable> keep <replaceable>points</replaceable>
                                    
<replaceable>object</replaceable> updateperiod <replaceable>milliseconds</replaceable>
                                               
<replaceable>object</replaceable> get

<replaceable>object</replaceable> names
            </command>
            </programlisting>
        </para>
        <refsect2>
            <title>channelHistory OPTIONS</title>
            <para>
                These options should be treated as readonly.  That is you should always
                <command>cget</command> them and never <command>configure</command> them.
            </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-period</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The number of milliseconds between each update of the object</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-channel</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The name of the EPICS channel monitored by this objecdt</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><option>-timebase</option></term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The time relative to which historical data time offsets are measured.
                        This is the output of a [clock seconds] command.  Note that time offsets
                        are floating point seconds.  It is possible to use a time offset in
                        conjunction with [clock format], a format string and a bit of arithmetic
                        to produce a timestamp for an individual data item that is exact to the
                        millisecond at which the data was updated.
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
                
        <refsect2>
            <title>channelHistory METHODS</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command><replaceable>object</replaceable> clear</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Clears all the historical data in the object.  On the stripchart this means
                            the trace for the channel managed by this element will vanish and then start
                            accumulating again as time passes.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            In a larger application, you could clear
                            the entire strip chart by iterating through the channelHistory elements you
                            created and clearing them all.  Since the channelHistory element object name
                            is the same as the stripchart element name, the BLT stripchart
                            <command>element names</command> can return alll the channel history objects
                            created <emphasis>as long as</emphasis> the chart only contains epics channels.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command><replaceable>object</replaceable> clearfirst <replaceable>points</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Removes the first <parameter>points</parameter> points of history data
                            from the object.  See the <command>keep</command> method for a better
                            way to keep the history data size under control.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command><replaceable>object</replaceable> keep <replaceable>points</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Requires that the history object retain at most <parameter>points</parameter>
                            data points.  After each update interval, if the history object contains
                            more than the specified number of points, the oldest points are discarded
                            until the correct number of points are retained.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command><replaceable>object</replaceable> updateperiod <replaceable>milliseconds</replaceable></command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Changes the update period to the <parameter>milliseconds</parameter> milliseconds.
                            this takes effect after the next update period.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command><replaceable>object</replaceable> get</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Returns the historical data for the parameter logged.  The historical data
                        is returned as a Tcl list of pairs.  Each pair contains a time offset (floating
                        point seconds) from the time base of the object (See the -timebase option), and
                        the value of the channel at that time.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This can be used to, e.g. perform analysis, logging or serialization for later
                        re-load, of the historical data.
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command><replaceable>object</replaceable> names</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The historical data are stored in two BLT vectors, a time and a data
                            vector.  This method returns a two element list consisting of the name
                            of the time and data vectors in that order.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </refsect2>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>BLT STRIPCHART</title>
        <para>
            This section summarizes the BLT stripchart widget.  This is intended just to provide
            an overview of the most useful options.  It is not intended as a complete
            document for that widget.  Complete documentation of the BLT strip chart widget can
            be found online at:
            <ulink url="http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_stripchart">http://man-wiki.net/index.php/N:blt_stripchart</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
            The stripchart widget is very flexible it can be configured via options, methods, and
            components.   Components are named entities that can be added to the stripchart and
            then manipulated via their own options and components.  The following component are
            supported:
        </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>axis</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Coordinate axes control the region of data displayed and how the
                            data are scaled.  Up to four axes (2 x and 2 y) can be displayed on the
                            chart.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>crosshairs</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>crosshairs can be defined to get a better idea of where the cursor is</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>element</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Elements are data point sets and their attributes.  Each channel added
                            to the chart creates an element.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>grid</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The grid extends major and minor ticks across the plotting area to make it
                            easier to read the location of points off the plot by eye.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>legend</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Legends display labels for the elements and their styles.  Note that while
                            the strip chart default label is the element name, the
                            <command>epicsStripChart addchannel</command> command labels the element's
                            entry in the legend with the EPICS channel name.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>marker</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Markers are used to annotate or highlight areas of the graph.
                            Many different marker types are supported including text, bitmaps,
                            polylines, images, polgons, and embedded widgets.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>pen</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Pens define attributes for elements.  They can be thought of as attribute
                            bundles that can be applied in a single configuration parameter.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>postscript</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The postscript component allows you to save the contents of the graph in
                            a postscript file as well as to configure the way in which that file is
                            produced.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <refsect2>
                <title>Key Stripchart options</title>
                <para>
                    This section provides a summary of a few of the more interesting, non-standard
                    options recognized by the strip chart widget.  See the online docs for complete
                    documentation.
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-halo <replaceable>pixels</replaceable></option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Specifies a maximum distance to consider when searching for
                                the closest data point  (see  the  element's closest operation below).
                                Data points further than pixels away are ignored.  The default is
                                0.5i.  This is used e.g. to process mouse hits in event bindings.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-height <replaceable>measure</replaceable></option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Specifies the requested height of widget.  The default is 4i.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-invertxy <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                               Indicates whether the placement X-axis and Y-axis should be inverted.
                               If boolean is  true,  the  X and Y axes are swapped.  The default is 0
                               (unswapped).
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-tile <replaceable>image</replaceable></option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Specifies  a tiled background.  If image isn't "", the background
                                is tiled using image.  Otherwise, the normal background color is
                                drawn.  Image must be an image  created
                                using the Tk image command.  The default is "".
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-title <replaceable>text</replaceable></option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Sets the title to <replaceable>text</replaceable>. If
                                <replaceable>text</replaceable> is "", no title will be displayed.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><option>-width <replaceable>measure</replaceable></option></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Specifies the requested width of the widget.  The default is 5i.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </refsect2>
            <refsect2>
                <title>Key Stripchart methods</title>
                <para>
                    This section is a summary of the most useful stripchart methods.
                    See the online manpage for the BLT Stripchart for more complete documentation.
                    (We don't bother to document configure and cget as these are 'well understood'
                    Tk methods).
                </para>
                <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>axis <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Manipulates axis components.   See the section "Stripchart components"
                                for more information about this.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>crosshairs <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Manipulates the crosshairs component of the stripchart.  See
                                the section "Stripchart components" below for more information.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>element <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Manipulates element components.  Note that channels become element
                                components of the stripchart.  See the section
                                "Stripchart components" below for more information.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>grid <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Manipulates the grid component of the stripchart.  See the section
                                "Stripchart components" below for more information.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>invtransform <replaceable>winX winY</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Performs a coordinate transform that maps the point defined by
                                (<replaceable>winX winY</replaceable>) into the graph real
                                coordinate system.  Returns the transformed X/Y coordinates.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>legend <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Manipulates the legend component of the strip chart widget.
                                 See the section
                                "Stripchart components" below for more information.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>marker <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Manipulates marker components of the strip chart widget.
                                 See the section
                                "Stripchart components" below for more information.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>postscript <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Manipulates the postscript snapshot component of the widget.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>transform <replaceable>x y</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Transforms the point (<replaceable>x y</replaceable>) specified
                            in graph coordinates to widget coordinates.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>xaxis | x2axis | yaxis | y2axis <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable></command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                Manipulates an axis component of the graph.
                                 See the section
                                "Stripchart components" below for more information.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
            </refsect2>
            <refsect2>
                <title>Stripchart components</title>
                <para>
                    This section describes the various stripchart components and how
                    to create and manipulate them.
                </para>
                <refsect3>
                <title>Stripchart axes</title>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Stripchart axes</title>
                    <para>
                        Four  coordinate  axes  are automatically created: two X-coordinate axes (x and x2)
                        and two Y-coordinate axes (y, and y2).  By default, the axis x is located in the
                        bottom margin, y in the left margin, x2 in the top margin, and y2 in the right margin.
                    </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <para>
                        An  axis consists of the axis line, title, major and minor ticks, and
                        tick labels.  Major ticks are drawn at uniform intervals along the axis.
                        Each tick is labeled with its coordinate value.  Minor ticks are drawn at uniform
                        intervals within major ticks.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The  range of the axis controls what region of data is plotted.
                        Data points outside the minimum and maximum limits of the axis are
                        not plotted.  By default, the minimum and maximum limits are determined
                        from  the  data,  but you can reset either limit.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        You can create and use several axes. To create an axis, invoke the
                        axis component and its create operation.
                        <programlisting>
                        # Create a new axis called "temperature"
                        .s axis create temperature
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        You  map  data  elements  to  an axis using the element's
                        <option>-mapy</option> and <option>-mapx</option> configuration options.
                        They specify the
                        coordinate axes an element is mapped onto.
                        <programlisting> 
                        # Now map the temperature data to this axis.
                        .s element create "temp" -xdata $x -ydata $tempData \
                                                 -mapy temperature
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        While you can have many axes, only four axes can be displayed
                        simultaneously.  They are drawn in each of the margins  surrounding
                        the plotting area.  The axes x and y are drawn in the bottom and
                        left margins. The axes x2 and y2 are drawn in top and right margins.
                        Only x and y are shown by default. Note that the axes can have  different
                        scales.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        To  display  a different axis, you invoke one of the following
                        components: xaxis, yaxis, x2axis, and y2axis.  The <command>use</command>
                        operation designates the axis to be drawn in the corresponding margin:
                        xaxis in  the  bottom,  yaxis  in  the left, x2axis in the top, and
                        y2axis in the right.
                        <programlisting>
                        # Display the axis temperature in the left margin.
                        .s yaxis use temperature
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        You  can configure axes in many ways. The axis scale can be linear or
                        logarithmic.  The values along the axis can either monotonically
                        increase or decrease.  If you need custom tick labels, you can specify
                        a  Tcl  procedure  to format  the  label  as you wish.
                        You can control how ticks are drawn, by changing the major
                        tick interval or the number of minor ticks.  You can define
                        non-uniform tick intervals, such as for time-series plots.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This section describes the major operations on the strip chart axis
                        component.  All of these are invoked using the form
                        <programlisting>
                        <command>
                        <replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> axis <replaceable>operation ...</replaceable>
                        </command>
                        </programlisting>
                        Where we will now describe the most useful operations.
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>create <replaceable>name ?options?</replaceable></command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Creates a new axis <parameter>name</parameter> the optional
                                    options configure the axis as per the configuration options
                                    described below.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>delete <replaceable>name</replaceable></command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Deletes an existing axis.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>invtransform <replaceable>name screenCoords</replaceable></command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Transforms <parameter>screenCoords</parameter> from the widget
                                    coordinate system to the axis coordinate system defined by
                                    the axis <parameter>name</parameter>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>names <replaceable>?pattern ...</replaceable></command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Returns the name of all defined axes that match at least one of
                                    the patterns provided.  Patterns can contain <firstterm>glob</firstterm>
                                    wildcard characters. If no pattern is provided the command
                                    operates as if there was a single pattern: <literal>*</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>transform <replaceable>axisName axisCoord</replaceable></command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Returns <parameter>axisCoord</parameter> transformed to widget
                                    coordinates using the transformation defined by the axis
                                    <parameter>axisName</parameter>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    <para>
                        Axes can be configured using the <command>configure</command> subcommand
                        and their configuration can be inquired using the <command>cget</command>
                        subcommand. For example:
                        <programlisting>
                            <command>
                        <replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> axis configure <replaceable>axisName ...</replaceable>
                            </command>
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        More useful configuration parameters for an axis include:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-logscale <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Indicates whether the scale of the axis is logarithmic
                                    or linear.  If <replaceable>boolean</replaceable>
                                    is true, the axis  is logarithmic.  The default scale is linear.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-majorticks <replaceable>ticklist</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies  where to display major axis ticks.  You can
                                    use this option to display ticks at non-uniform intervals.
                                    <replaceable>ticklist</replaceable> is a list of axis
                                    coordinates designating the location of  major  ticks.
                                    No  minor  ticks  are  drawn.   If <replaceable>ticklist</replaceable>
                                    is "", major ticks will be automatically computed. The
                                    default is "".
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-max <replaceable>value</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Sets the maximum limit of axisName.  Any data point
                                    greater than value is not displayed.  If  value is "",
                                    the maximum limit is calculated using the largest data
                                    value.  The default is "".
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-min <replaceable>value</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Sets  the  minimum limit of axisName. Any data point
                                    less than value is not displayed.  If value is "", the
                                    minimum limit is calculated using the smallest data value.
                                    The default is "".
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-minorticks <replaceable>ticklist</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies where to display minor axis ticks.  You can
                                    use this option to  display  minor  ticks  at non-uniform
                                    intervals. <replaceable>ticklist</replaceable> is a
                                    list of real values, ranging from 0.0 to 1.0, designating the
                                    placement of a minor tick.  No minor ticks are drawn if the
                                    -majortick  option  is  also  set.   If minorList is "",
                                    minor ticks will be automatically computed. The default is "".
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-shiftby <replaceable>value</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies how much to automatically shift the range of the axis.
                                    When the  new  data  exceeds  the
                                    current  axis maximum, the maximum is increased in increments
                                    of <replaceable>value</replaceable>.
                                    You can use this option to prevent the axis limits from
                                    being recomputed at each new time point. If
                                    <replaceable>value</replaceable>  is  0.0,  then  no
                                    automatic shifting is done. The default is 0.0.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-title <replaceable>text</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Sets the title of the axis. If <replaceable>text</replaceable>
                                    is "", no axis title will be displayed.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                        
                    <para>
                        The axis positions at the bottom, top, left and right can be selected and
                        manipulated using the <command>xaxis xaxis1 yaxis yaxis2</command> commands
                        respectively.  In this document, we only describe how to select an axis for
                        use in that position:
                        <programlisting>
                            <command>
                <replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> {xaxis | xaxis1 | yaxis | yaxis1}  use <replaceable>axisName</replaceable>
                            </command>
                        </programlisting>
                        For example, to create an axis named george and display it at the top part of the
                        graph:
                        <programlisting>
                            <command>
                <replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> axis create george
                <replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> xaxis1 use george
                            </command>
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                </refsect3>
                <refsect3>
                    <title>Stripchart crosshairs</title>
                    <formalpara><title>Crosshairs</title>
                    <para>
                        This section describes the crosshairs component of the stripchart.
                        Cross hairs consist of two intersecting lines (one vertical and
                        one horizontal) drawn completely across the plotting area.
                        They are used to position the mouse in relation to the
                        coordinate axes.  Cross hairs differ from line
                        markers in that they are implemented using XOR drawing primitives.
                        This means that they can be quickly drawn and
                        erased without redrawing the entire strip chart.
                    </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <para>
                        There is only a single crosshair.  To turn crosshairs on for the
                        stripchart .stripchart:
                        <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> crosshairs on</command>
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Similarly to turn crosshairs off:
                        <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> crosshairs off</command>
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                </refsect3>
                <refsect3>
                    <title>Stripchart elements (traces)</title>
                    <para>
                        Elements are data sets that are drawn on the stripchart.
                        In the case of the <command>epicsStripChart</command> elements
                        are created using the <command>addchannel</command> method.
                        It is also possible to intermix elements created 'manualy'.
                        We will not document how to do this. You will need to
                        read the online BLT Stripchart widget to see how to do this.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        When you create an element via <command>addchannel</command> the
                        name of the element will be returned and can be captured via e.g.:
                        <programlisting>
                            <command>
set elementName [<replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> addchannel <replaceable>someChannel</replaceable>]
                            </command>
                        </programlisting>
                        Once this is done you can use <varname>$elementName</varname>
                        wherever an element name is
                        required to refer to that element.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Elements can be configured with various options, and their configurations
                        queried via e.g.:
                        <programlisting>
                            <command>
<replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> element configure <replaceable>name options...</replaceable>
<replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> element cget <replaceable>name option-name</replaceable>
                            </command>  
                        </programlisting>
                        A useful subset of the options is:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-activepen <replaceable>penName</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies pen to use to draw active element.  If
                                    <replaceable>penName</replaceable> is "",
                                    no active elements will  be  drawn.
                                    The default is activeLine.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-color <replaceable>color</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Sets the color of the traces connecting the data points.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-linewidth <replaceable>pixels</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies the line width of the element in pixels.  If
                                    <parameter>pixels</parameter> is zero, no line will be drawn,
                                    between symbols.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-mapx</option> <parameter>axisName</parameter></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Selects the X-axis to map the element's X-coordinates onto.
                                    <parameter>axisName</parameter> must be the  name  of  an  axis.
                                    The default is <literal>xaxis</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-mapy</option>  <parameter>axisName</parameter></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Selects the Y-axis to map the element's Y-coordinates onto.
                                    <parameter>axisName</parameter>
                                    must be the name of an axis. The default is yaxis.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-smooth <parameter>style</parameter></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies how connecting line segments are drawn between data points.
                                    <parameter>style</parameter> can be either
                                    <literal>linear</literal>,
                                    <literal>step</literal>,
                                    <literal>natural</literal>  , or
                                    <literal>quadratic</literal>.
                                    If <parameter>style</parameter> is <literal>linear</literal>,
                                    a single line segment is drawn, connecting both
                                    data points. When <parameter>style</parameter> is <literal>step</literal>,
                                    two line segments are drawn. The first is a horizontal line  segment
                                    which steps the next x-coordinate.  The second is a vertical line,
                                    moving to the next y-coordinate.  Both
                                    <literal>natural</literal> and
                                    <literal>quadratic</literal> generate multiple segments between
                                    data  points.   If  <literal>natural</literal>,
                                    the  segments  are  generated using a cubic spline.
                                    If <literal>quadratic</literal>, a quadratic spline is used.  The
                                    default is linear.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-symbol <parameter>symbol</parameter></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies the symbol for data points.
                                    <parameter>symbol</parameter> can be either
                                    <literal>square</literal>, <literal>circle</literal>,
                                    <literal>diamond</literal>,  <literal>plus</literal>,
                                    <literal>cross</literal>, <literal>splus</literal>,
                                    <literal>scross</literal>,  <literal>triangle</literal>,
                                    <literal>""</literal>  (where  no symbol is drawn), or a bitmap.
                                    Bitmaps are specified as
                                    <literal>"source ?mask?"</literal>,
                                    where source is the name of the bitmap, and mask is the  bitmap's
                                    optional  mask.
                                    The default is <literal>circle</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    <para>
                        Element are invoked using the following general form:
                        <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> element <replaceable>methodname ...</replaceable></command>
                        </programlisting>
                        Where the most useful methodnames and their parameters are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>closest <replaceable>x y varName ?option value?... ?elemName?...</replaceable></command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Finds  the  data point closest to the window coordinates
                                    <parameter>x</parameter> and <parameter>y</parameter> in the element
                                    <parameter>elemName</parameter>.  <parameter>ElemName</parameter>
                                    is the
                                    name of an element, that must not be hidden.
                                    If no elements are specified, then all visible elements  are
                                    searched.   It  returns  via  the array variable varName
                                    the name of the closest element, the index of its
                                    closest point, and the graph coordinates of the point.
                                    Returns 0, if no data point  within  the  threshold
                                    distance can be found, otherwise 1 is returned.
                                    The following option-value pairs are available.
                                    <variablelist>
                                        <varlistentry>
                                            <term><option>-halo <replaceable>distance</replaceable></option></term>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    Specifies  a  threshold  distance where selected
                                                    data points are ignored.  
                                                    <parameter>distance</parameter> is a valid screen
                                                    distance, such as 2 or 1.2i.  If this option isn't
                                                    specified, then it defaults to the value of  the
                                                    stripchart's <option>-halo</option> option.
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </varlistentry>
                                        <varlistentry>
                                            <term><option>-interpolate <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    Indicates that both the data points and interpolated
                                                    points along the line segment formed should be
                                                    considered.  If
                                                    <parameter>boolean</parameter> is <literal>true</literal>,
                                                    the closest line segment will be selected instead of
                                                    the  closest
                                                    point. If this option isn't specified,
                                                    <parameter>boolean</parameter> defaults to <literal>0</literal>
                                                    which is a Tcl <literal>false</literal> value.
                                                    </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </varlistentry>
                                    </variablelist>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>exists <replaceable>elemName</replaceable></command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Returns 1 if an element elemName currently exists and 0 otherwise.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>names <replaceable>?pattern? ...</replaceable></command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Returns the elements matching one or more pattern.  If no pattern
                                    is given, the names of all  elements  is returned.  Note that if
                                    the widget is only displaying epics channels, these names are the
                                    same as the names of the channelHistory objects that contain and
                                    maintain the data that is being plotted.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                </refsect3>
                <refsect3>
                    <title>Stripchart grids</title>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Stripchart Grids</title>
                    <para>
                        Stripchart grids extend the tick marks on the axes across the entire face of
                        the graph part of the widget.  grids make it easier to read a point off the
                        graph.
                    </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <para>
                        Grids have configuration options that are set and gotten via e.g.
                        <programlisting>
                            
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> grid configure  <replaceable>options...</replaceable></command>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable>grid cget <replaceable>option-name</replaceable></command>

                        </programlisting>                                                                                  
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Grids also have methods that are invoked via e.g:
                        <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> grid <replaceable>methodname ...</replaceable></command>
                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The key configuration options for the grid are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-color</option> <replaceable>color</replaceable></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Sets the color of the grid lines.  The default is black.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-mapx</option> <replaceable>xAxis</replaceable></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies the X-axis to display grid lines.
                                    <parameter>XAxis</parameter> must be the name of an axis.
                                    The default is  <literal>xaxis</literal>.
                                    </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-mapy</option> <replaceable>yAxis</replaceable></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies the Y-axis to display grid lines.
                                    <parameter>YAxis</parameter> must be the name of an axis.
                                    The default is <literal>y</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    <para>
                        In addition to the <command>configure</command> and <command>cget</command>
                        methods that manipulate grid configuration parameters. the two main
                        methods are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>off</command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Turns off the display the grid lines.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><command>on</command></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Turns on the display the grid lines.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                </refsect3>
                <refsect3>
                    <title>Stripchart legends</title>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Stripchart legends</title>
                    <para>
                        The  legend  displays  a  list of the data elements.  Each
                        entry consists of the element's symbol and label.  The
                        legend can appear in any margin (the default location is
                        in the right margin).  It can also  be  positioned  any where within
                        the plotting area.
                    </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <para>
                        The legend documentation we will provide here are the legend options
                        that can all be configured or queried via e.g.:
                        <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> configure <replaceable>options...</replaceable></command>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> cget <replaceable>option-name</replaceable></command>
                        </programlisting>
                        Where the most common options are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-hide <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Indicates  whether the legend should be displayed.
                                    If <parameter>boolean</parameter> is true, the legend
                                    will not be drawn.
                                    The default is false, allowing the legend to be visible.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-postition <replaceable>pos</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies where the legend is drawn.   If <parameter>pos</parameter>
                                    is <literal>left</literal>,
                                    <literal>left</literal>, <literal>top</literal>, or
                                    <literal>bottom</literal>, the legend is drawn in the
                                    specified margin.  If <parameter>pos</parameter>
                                    is <literal>plotarea</literal>, then the legend is drawn
                                    inside the plotting area.  If  <parameter>pos</parameter>  is
                                    in  the  form <literal>"@x,y"</literal>, where
                                    <literal>x</literal> and <literal>y</literal> are
                                    the window coordinates, the legend is drawn in the plotting
                                    area at the specified coordinates.  The default is right.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                </refsect3>
                <refsect3>
                    <title>Stripchart Pens</title>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Stripchart Pens</title>
                        <para>
                            Stripchart pen components are bundles of attributes that can be
                            applied to elements (traces).  The construction and manipulation of
                            pens is an advanced topic refer to the blt::stripchart online manpage
                            for information about this component.
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                </refsect3>
                <refsect3>
                    <title>Stripchart Postcript output</title>
                    <para>
                        The postscript component support the generation of a postscript file
                        that allows printing the contents of the plot.  The most commonly
                        used postcript method is:
                        <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> postscript output <filename>filename</filename> <replaceable>options...</replaceable></command>
                        </programlisting>
                        Where the most common options are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-colormode <replaceable>mode</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies how to output color information.
                                    <parameter>Mode</parameter> must be either
                                    <literal>color</literal> (for full color output),
                                    <literal>gray</literal>
                                    (convert all colors to their gray-scale equivalents) or
                                    <literal>mono</literal> (convert foreground  colors  to  black
                                    and background colors to white).
                                  The default mode is <literal>color</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-landscape <replaceable>boolean</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    If
                                    <parameter>boolean</parameter>  is  true, this specifies the
                                    printed area is to be rotated 90 degrees.  In non-rotated
                                    output the X-axis of the printed area runs along the short
                                    dimension of the page (``portrait'' orientation);  in  rotated
                                    output the X-axis runs along the long dimension of the page
                                    (``landscape'' orientation).  Defaults to 0.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>  
                    </variablelist>
                </refsect3>
                <refsect3>
                    <title>Stripchart Markers</title>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Stripchart Markers</title>
                    <para>
                        Markers are simple drawing procedures used to annotate or highlight
                        areas of the strip chart.  Markers have various types: text strings,
                        bitmaps, images, connected lines, windows, or polygons.
                    </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <para>
                        While the use of markers can be useful in many application we do not
                        want to reproduce the entire blt::stripchart manpage about markers here.
                        We will only show how to create markers of the various sorts and
                        what each marker type's configuration options are.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        All markers understand a <option>-coords</option> option that
                        contains a list of coordinates.  The number of coordinates required
                        and their meaning depends on the marker type.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        All markers understand a <option>-name</option> option that provides a
                        unique name for the marker.  If not provided, the widget will generate a
                        unique name for you.
                    </para>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Creating a bitmap marker</title>
                        <para>
                            A bitmap marker displays a bitmap.  The size of the bitmap is
                            controlled by the number of coordinates  specified.
                            If  two coordinates, they specify the position of the top-left corner
                            of the bitmap.  The bitmap retains its normal width and height.
                            If four coordinates, the first and second pairs of coordinates represent
                            the  corners  of the bitmap.  The bitmap will be stretched or
                            reduced as necessary to fit into the bounding rectangle.
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <para>
                        Bitmap markers are created with the marker's create operation in the form:
                        <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> marker create bitmap  <replaceable>?options?</replaceable></command>
                        </programlisting>
                        This command returns the name of the marker created.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Bitmap specific options of interest are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-bitmap <replaceable>bitmap</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies  the bitmap to be displayed.  If
                                    <parameter>bitmap</parameter> is "", the
                                    marker will not be displayed.  The default is  "".
                                    </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-mask <replaceable>mask</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies a mask for the bitmap to be displayed. This mask is
                                    a bitmap itself, denoting  the  pixels  that are transparent.
                                    If <parameter>mask</parameter> is "", all pixels of the bitmap will be
                                    drawn.  The default is "".
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-rotate <replaceable>theta</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    The marker is first rotated and then placed according
                                    to its anchor position.   The  default  rotation  is
                                    0.0.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Image markers</title>
                        <para>
                             A image marker displays an image.  Image markers are created with the marker's
                            create operation in the form:
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> marker create image -image <replaceable>image-name</replaceable></command>
                    </programlisting>
                    <para>
                        The coordinates for an image have the same meaning as for a bitmap.
                    </para>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Line Markers</title>
                        <para>
                            A line marker displays one or more connected line segments.
                            Line markers are created with marker's create operation in the form:
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> marker create line <replaceable>?options?</replaceable></command>
                    </programlisting>
                    <para>
                        The coordinates in this case are the coordinates of the vertices of the
                        polyline that make up the marker.  There must be at least four coordinates,
                        x1,y1, and x2,y2 of a single line segment, however there can be additional
                        points to add additional line segments to the marker.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The commonly used options for the line marker are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-foreground <replaceable>color</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Sets the foreground color.  The default foreground color is black.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-linewidth <replaceable>pixels</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Sets the width of the lines.  The default width is 0.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Polygon Markers</title>
                        <para>
                            These are essentially Line markers with an added line connecting the last
                            point to the first point, however just to be perverse, some of
                            the options have different names.
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> marker create polygon <replaceable>options...</replaceable></command>
                    </programlisting>
                    <para>
                        Key options are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-fill <replaceable>color</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Sets the fill color of the polygon.  If
                                    <parameter>color</parameter> is "", then the interior of
                                    the polygon is transparent.  The
                                    default is white.
                                    </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-outline <replaceable>color</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Sets the color of the outline of the polygon.  The default is black.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Text Markers</title>
                        <para>
                            A text marker displays a string of characters on one or more lines
                            of text.  Embedded newlines cause line breaks.
                            They may be used to annotate regions of the strip chart.   One pair of
                            coordinates must be supplied with the marker to specify where the
                            text is modified by the <option>-anchor</option> options.
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <para>
                        Text markers are created as follows:
                        <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> marker create text <replaceable>?option? ...</replaceable></command>
                        </programlisting>
                        Where the most commonly used options are:
                    </para>
                    <variablelist>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-anchor <replaceable>anchor</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <replaceable>Anchor</replaceable>
                                    tells how to position the text relative to the positioning
                                    point for  the  text.  For  example,  if
                                    <replaceable>anchor</replaceable>  is
                                    <literal>center</literal> then
                                    the text is
                                    centered on the point; if
                                    <replaceable>anchor</replaceable> is <literal></literal>
                                    then the text
                                    will be drawn such that the top center point of the rectangular
                                    region occupied by the text will be at the positioning point.
                                    This default is <literal>center</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-foreground <replaceable>color</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Sets the foreground color of the text. The default is black.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-justify <replaceable>justify</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Specifies how the text should be justified.
                                    This matters only when the marker contains more than one line
                                    of text.
                                    <replaceable>Justify</replaceable>
                                    must be <literal>left</literal>, <literal>right</literal>, or
                                    <literal>center</literal>.  The default is <literal>center</literal>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-rotate  <replaceable>theta</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies the number of degrees to rotate the text.
                                    <parameter>Theta</parameter> is a real  number  representing
                                    the  angle  of
                                    rotation.   The  marker  is first rotated along its center and
                                    is then drawn according to its anchor position. The default is 0.0.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                        <varlistentry>
                            <term><option>-text <replaceable>text</replaceable></option></term>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Specifies the text of the marker.  The exact way the text is
                                    displayed may be affected  by  other  options such as
                                    <option>-anchor</option> or
                                    <option>-rotate</option>.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Window markers</title>
                        <para>
                            Window markers allow you to place other widgets on the
                            stripchart.  The idea is that you create a widget that is a
                            child of the stripchart.  You then add it as a window marker
                            using the coordinates to specify the position of the widget.
                            e.g:
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                    <programlisting>
<command><replaceable>.stripchart</replaceable> marker create window -window <replaceable>.stripchart.w</replaceable> ...</command>
                    </programlisting>
                </refsect3>
            </refsect2>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>EXAMPLES</title>
        <para>
        </para>
    </refsect1>
    <refsect1>
        <title>SEE ALSO</title>
        <para>

        </para>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>



</article>
</book>